For Task 40 we have to design a binary predicate h
that when we interpret it as a function, it takes a
list of lists, reverses each inner list, and then
concatenates the results into one single list.
So, if you, for example, have this
invocation here where we have a list
that has this list [a, b] and this list
[c, d, e], and then the result should be
b, a which is the reverse of the first list
and e, d, c which is the reversed second list.
And to do so we shall not use
more than two program clauses.
And we should make use of these two functions
or two predicates append and reverse.
If we take a look at what these
do, they do the obvious thing.
Append is a predicate with three
arguments, so if we have a list [1, 2, 3]
and a list [4, 5] then we can ask for the third
thing and we get [1, 2, 3, 4, 5] as we would expect.
You can also ask for the
second parameter, obviously.
If we say, okay, [1, 2, 3]
and then [4, 5] and so on.
Reverse works basically the same way, we have
a binary predicate, and it reverses the list.
So you can also "unreverse" the list
by inverting where we put the variable.
We can use these two predicates
to help us implement h.
Okay, so you should have two clauses. So first
of all, we probably need some sort of base case.
Some clause that is always true for h.
So the obvious one is if we have an empty list,
then the result should also be the empty list.
Right? Because there are no inner lists
that we need to reverse and concatenate.
And so there aren't any elements
in the resulting list either.
Okay, so probably the second clause is something
like we have a list with at least one element,
and then we have some result,
let's call it Ys for now.
And then there are some conditions.
So first off we should probably
use reverse at some point, right?
We should reverse X and make it Y.
Okay, this does not do anything
useful right now because Y is
not determined or could be anything now.
We need to say what Ys is.
Okay, so we say we append our new Y to something.
Let's put a blank in there at the moment.
And then this is our Ys.
Okay, so now what do we need to append Y to
in order to implement the desired behavior?
Well, we want to basically
do the recursion on Xs.
So you can say, put Xs into h,
and this results in some list Zs.
And then onto this list, we append Y.
And that gives us our final result.
Ys the result of appending Y
to Zs, and that comes from
our recursive call, and Y
is obtained by reversing X.
Okay, so um let's load this up.
So, let's first check the example
which should hold, and we get true.
Okay, that's nice.
Now let's take a look at another example.
We have a list of [1, 2, 3] and [4, 5]
and we want to know what is the result of this.
Okay, it's exactly that first list
reversed and then the second list reversed.
We can also look at what the Haskell definition
of this function would look like and then
compare that to the Prolog version we just wrote.
Okay, so here's how you could implement this
in Haskell in the most straightforward way.
h is a function from a [[a]] to a [a].
And for [] this is [] and if we
have a first list and a list of
more lists, we reverse the first list
and prepend it to the recursive call.
Okay, and if we restructure this, such that
we don't have nested calls, we can basically
say we have some zs which is reverse xs ...
No, let's call it ys and
we have some yss which is the recursive call.
And then we have some zs which is just this.
And then the result is just zs.
Right? It's a really simple refactoring
to eliminate any nested function calls.
If we now compare this to
what we have written here.
We've used slightly different variables, but if
we change this, flip around the variables a bit
like this, use the double
s's here too, like this.
Then we can see that this is actually
a straightforward translation.
There is a one-to-one correspondence.
We have this h call which is right here
we call h of xss and the result is yss.
We call reverse of xs and the result is
ys and we call append on ys and yss.
And append is an infix operator in Haskell
so this looks a little bit different.
And the result then is zs which is the
overall result of our function here.
And in the same way, we can shift these
definitions around. We can, in principle,
use a different ordering
of these conditions here.
But even though in the declarative
semantics this will not
change the meaning, in the operational semantics
of Prolog this changes the meaning because
if we, for example, move 'append' to
the front, we will have a problem.
Let's see our example is still true.
But if we then actually want to know what
X is and not just know in advance, then
we get an error because there's non-termination
because Prolog first tries to figure out
what kind of possible splits
for these variables we have.
Because at this point, when we have this query,
we instantiate Xs with [a, b] and Xss with
the list containing this
second list and Zs is unknown.
But this means that Ys, Yss, and Zs are
all unknown in this call to append since
Yss is only defined here and Ys only here, or
can be resolved more easily, we should say.
So we then just do append
basically of X, Y, and Z.
This obviously is a call that
can give you some results, but really no
useful ones since it will just say here are
a bunch of more variables you need to instantiate
and even more variables on top of that.
And it's easy to see why this
results in non-termination.